Finding Aid for Museum of Art (University of Michigan) records, 1946-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Photographs, 1913-1998
  The 1913 images of the galleries in Alumni Memorial Hall depict the Mum Show held in November of that year where pieces of the university's collection of sculpture were displayed in the building's apse with flowers. The photographs were taken by George R. Swain, university photographer from 1913 to 1947, and are identified in more detail by Swain in an index of his work. The six images are on glass plate negatives (one of which is cracked) but there are prints of two and all but one has been scanned.
  - Exterior building (Box 23)
  - Galleries
    - University Library (Box 23)
    - Alumni Memorial Hall
      - (8x10 glass plate negatives, 4x5 copy negatives, na18507-na19511), 1913 (Box 23)
      - 1925 (Box 23)
      - 1950s (Box 23)
      - 1960s (Box 23)
      - 1970s (Box 23)
      - 1980s (Box 23)
      - 1990s (Box 23)
      - undated (Box 23)
  - Events
    - Acquisitions (Box 23)
    - Concerts, etc. (Box 23)
  - Staff (Box 23)
    (see also: Docents-Photographs, folder 3)
- Publicity, 1986-2001
  The Publicity series (1986-2001; 2.3 linear ft.) has been artificially arranged into two subseries: Exhibitions and Topical Files. These exhibition files, the earliest of which dates only to 1986, are not nearly as comprehensive as the Exhibition Files series. There is likely some overlap within files since both series contain clippings, but the publicity files have a more extensive collection of these. Also included are object photographs for press releases; educational materials for teacher or parent packets; and correspondence.
  Topical Files are arranged alphabetically and document a variety of the UMMA's programs: Concert Series, Docents, Family Programs, Friends of the Museum of Art and Special Events. These files contain clippings related to particular programs and events; but others can be found under 'Clippings' and 'General' files. Additionally, there is documentation of an evaluation of the mission of the museum as a whole in the early 1990s and a 1991 proposal for a museums complex on campus which was to provide a new facility for both the UMMA and the Kelsey Museum of Archaeology.
  - Exhibitions
    - "The Rising of a New Moon: A Century of Tabwa Art,", April 18-July 27, 1986 (Box 24)
    - "Images of the Native American West,", October 31-November 12, 1989 (Box 24)
    - "Twelve Artists from the German Democratic Republic,", February 9-March 25, 1990 (Box 24)
    - "Centuries of Chinese Clay: Early Ceramics from the Domino's Pizza Collection,", September 16-October 21, 1990 (Box 24)
      (includes object photographs and transparency)
    - "Bellows and Diebenkorn: Prints from the Doris Sloan Collection,", September 21-November 11, 1990 (Box 24)
    - "Sculpture and Drawings by Reuben Nakian" (Armenian Odyssey II), September 23-November 23, 1990 (Box 24)
      (includes photographs of opening reception)
    - "Lorna Simpson,", October 19-December 2, 1990 (Box 24)
    - "City and Country in French Prints, 1850-1990,", October 19-December 23, 1990 (Box 24)
    - "Landscape Drawings and Prints from the Collection of Rudolf L. Baumfeld,", November 9-December 23, 1990 (Box 24)
    - "Antique Toys and Banks from the Collection of Bob Lyons,", November 24, 1990-January 27, 1991 (Box 24)
    - "Chinese New Year Posters,", January 12-March 3, 1991 (Box 24)
    - "Lessons from the East,", January 26-March 10, 1991 (Box 24)
    - "Greece vs. Rome: The Search for the Classical Spirit,", March 16-April 28, 1991 (Box 24)
    - "The Female Gaze,", February 9-March 24, 1991 (Box 24)
    - "Pudlo: Thirty Years of Drawing,", March 23-May 19, 1991; 2 folders (Box 24)
      (includes photographs and negative)
    - "Travel Sketches by Albert Kahn,", March 30-June 9, 1991 (Box 24)
    - "Margarete Baum: Recent Paintings,", April 5-May 26, 1991 (Box 24)
    - "Photographs by Walker Evans,", May 11-July 7, 1991 (Box 24)
    - "The Edwards Ledger Drawings: Folk Art by Arapaho Warriors,", March 20-May 2, 1992 (Box 24)
      (includes teachers' packet material)
    - "African Art from the Permanent Collection: A Celebration,", February 13-August 1, 1993 (Box 24)
      (includes parents' packet material)
    - "In Focus: Guercino's Esther,", March 7-May 16, 1993 (Box 24)
      (includes object photograph)
    - "German Expressionist Graphics from the Museum Collection," (includes object photographs), September 11-December 5, 1993 (Box 24)
    - "Hannah Höch: Collages,", October 9-November 28, 1993 (Box 24)
      (includes object photographs and negatives)
    - "The Fair View: Representations of the World's Columbian Exhibition of 1893,", October 30-December 31, 1993 (Box 24)
    - "Socialist Realism: Twentieth-Century Paintings from the Soviet Union,", December 4, 1993-February 27, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Larry Cressman: An Installation,", December 11, 1993-March 6, 1994 (Box 24)
      (includes artist photograph)
    - "Nijinsky Dancing: Photographs from the Roger Pryor Dodge Collection,", December 18, 1993-February 27, 1994 (Box 24)
    - Picasso and Gris Paintings from Carey Walker Foundation (Gift to UMMA), January 1994 (Box 24)
      (includes object photographs and slides)
    - "James Tissot: Prints from the Aldrich Collection,", January 15-March 6, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Driven to Abstraction: Art of the Twentieth Century" (installation), February 11-Mid-Summer 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Paintings by Mark Rothko: 1945-1969,", March 5-May 8, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Cubism and Its Legacy,", March 12-May 29, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Photographs by Howard Bond,", March 19-June 12, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Whistler: Prosaic Views, Poetic Vision: Works on Paper from the University of Michigan Museum of Art,", March 26-May 22, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "The Return to Figuration,", May 20-September 4, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Reflections of the Everyday World: Seventeenth-Century Dutch Prints," (includes object photographs), June 10-August 21, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "A Closer Look,", 1994-1995 (Box 24)
    - "Transition and Transformation: African Art of the In-Between,", September 1994-June 1995 (Box 24)
    - "The Jade Studio: Masterpieces of Ming and Qing Painting from the Wong Nan-P'ing Collection,", September 10-November 20, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Beyond Empire: Artistic Expressions of Byzantium,", September 17-October 30, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Isamu Noguchi: Exploration and Collaboration,", September 24-November 13, 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Staffs of Life: African Rods, Staffs and Sceptres from the Coudron Collection,", December 3, 1994-February 26, 1995 (Box 24)
      (includes donor photographs)
    - "Adriaen van Ostade: Etchings of Peasant Life in Holland's Golden Age,", September 2-October 15, 1995 (Box 24)
      (includes object photograph and negatives)
    - "John Stephenson: After the Fire, A Retrospective,", November 4, 1995-January 15, 1996 (Box 24)
      (includes object and artist photographs)
    - Fiftieth Anniversary Year, 1996-1997 (Box 24)
    - "Komar, Melamid and Renee,", September 9-October 13, 1996 (Box 24)
    - "Venice, Traditions Transformed: Works from the Sarah Campbell Blaffer Foundation and the University of Michigan,", September 21, 1996-January 21, 1997 (Box 24)
    - "Michigan Collectors,", February 8-April 13, 1997 (Box 24)
    - "When Time Began to Rant and Rage: Figurative Painting from Twentieth-Century Ireland,", September 25, 1999-January 2, 2000; 2 folders (Box 24)
    - "Transparent/Opaque: An Installation by Annette Lawrence,", March 18-April 16, 2000 (Box 24)
    - "Still Time: Photographs by Sally Mann,", April 15-June 11, 2000 (Box 24)
    - "The White House Collection of American Crafts,", July 1-October 22, 2000 (Box 24)
    - "Video Art by Chris Doyle," (part of "VideoCulture: Three Decades of Video Art"), September 7-October 4, 2000 (Box 24)
    - "The Villa of the Mysteries in Pompeii: Ancient Ritual, Modern Muse,", October 1-November 19, 2000 (Box 24)
    - "Seeing is Healing? The Visual Arts of Medicine,", October 7-December 3, 2000 (Box 24)
    - "William Kentridge: Weighing.. .and Wanting,", November 18, 2000-January 17, 2001 (Box 24)
    - "Casting Shadows: Photographs by Edward West,", December 2, 2000-January 28, 2001 (Box 24)
      (includes object slides)
  - Topical Files
    - Advertising
      - 1990-1991 (Box 25)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 25)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 25)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 25)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 25)
    - Clippings
      - Concerts and programs, 1971-1988 (Box 25)
      - Exhibitions, 1970-1973 (Box 25)
      - General, 1968-1987 (Box 25)
    - Calendars/Schedules, 1994-1996 (Box 25)
    - Concert Series
      - 1990-1991 (Box 25)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 25)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 25)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 25)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 25)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 25)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 25)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 25)
    - Development
      - Capital Campaign, 1992 (Box 25)
      - Grants (Institute of Museum Services), 1990-1995 (Box 25)
    - Docents
      - Fall docent tours, 1990-1992 (Box 25)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 25)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 25)
      - 1994-1995 Doris Sloan Memorial Lecture, November 12, 1994 (Box 25)
    - Education
      - Correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 25)
      - Community Education Evaluation, 1992 (Box 25)
    - Family Programs
      - 1990-1991 (Box 25)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 25)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 25)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 25)
    - Friends of the Museum
      - 1990-1991 (Box 25)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 25)
      - 1992-1993 "Collectors' Seminar," January 28 and February 4, 1993 (Box 25)
      - 1993-1994
        - Spring Event 1993 ("The Automobile as Art: Our Culture in Motion"), May 23, 1993 (Box 25)
        - "Club Dada,", October 16, 1993 (Box 25)
          (includes photographs and audiocassette)
        - General (Box 25)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 25)
    - Lectures, 1978-1988 (Box 25)
    - Long Range Planning Team, 1994-1996 (Box 25)
    - Mission Team, 1992-1993 (Box 25)
    - Museum Gift Shop
      - 1991-1992 (Box 25)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 25)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 25)
    - Museum Practice Program, 1991-1992 (Box 25)
    - Museums complex, 1991 (Box 25)
    - Publications
      - 1990-1991
        - Annual Report (Box 25)
        - Bi-Monthly Calendar (Box 25)
      - Rembrandt (1606-69) bibliography, 1991-1992 (Box 25)
        (in connection with "Rembrandt and the Bible" exhibition)
    - Special Events
      - 1990-1991 Christine Mather lecture, June 22, 1991 (Box 25)
      - Asian Painting Conservation Symposium, 1992 (Box 25)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 25)
      - 1994-1995
        - "An Evening at the Museum,", 1994-1995 (Box 25)
        - Medieval Theatre Project-"King Robert of Sicily,", January-March 1995 (Box 25)
          (performed in connection with "Divine Illuminations: Devotional Books of the Middle Ages" exhibition)
    - Theater
      - Stratford Festival, 1993 (Box 25)
      - General, 1993-1994 (Box 25)
    - Travel Program: "The Road to Santiago,", 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Visitor survey, 1996; undated (Box 26)
    - General
      - 1991-1992 (Box 26)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 26)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 26)
      - 1999
- Museum Practice Program, 1962-2000
  The Museum Practice Program series (1962-2000; 0.5 linear ft.) documents the museum's training program from its inception in the 1960s. It includes information about the curriculum, admission and requirements; lists of participants over the years and their placements in the museum field; and proposals and notes regarding changes to the program during the 1990s. Further discussion of these revisions, which involved launching a more interdisciplinary program not limited to the history of art in 2003, can be found within the correspondence files. Also of interest are course lecture notes written by Charles Sawyer during the program's first decade. A symposium held in 1979 on "American Museums in the Last Quarter of the Twentieth Century" served as a reunion for program graduates and a tribute to Charles Sawyer as well. This file contains correspondence between graduates and Mary Ann "Cricket" Swain, then Associate Chairman of the program; correspondence with Millard Rogers, Director of the Cincinnati Art Museum, who originated the idea for the event; and a thank-you letter from Sawyer to those who participated. The 'Correspondence-Students & staff' file includes reminiscences of Sawyer prompted by the symposium.
  - Correspondence
    - 1962-1990 (Box 26)
    - 1991-2000 (Box 26)
    - Students and staff, 1979-1980 (Box 26)
  - Program participants (Box 26)
  - Committee, 1968-1990 (Box 26)
  - Curriculum, 1964-2000 (Box 26)
  - Program revisions, 1991-2000 (Box 26)
  - Courses
    - Museum Seminar 207 and 208, 1959-1960 (Box 26)
    - Museum Practice 607 (Art Museum Philosophy and Practice)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 26)
      - 1963 (Box 26)
      - 1964 (Box 26)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 26)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 26)
      - 1967 (Box 26)
      - 1968 (Box 26)
      - 1969 (Box 26)
      - 1970 (Box 26)
      - undated (Box 26)
    - Museum Practice 612-Proposals for American Historical Institutions, 1972 (Box 26)
  - Internships
    - Henry Ford Museum, 1972 (Box 26)
    - Smith College Museum of Art, 1972-1976 (Box 26)
    - Toledo Museum of Art, 1973-1977 (Box 26)
  - Museum of Art exhibitions, 1962-1989 (Box 26)
  - Funding (Box 26)
  - Symposium: ["American Museums in the Last Quarter of the Twentieth Century"] 1979 (see also: Museum Practice Program-Correspondence-Students and staff, 1979-1980) (Box 26)
  - American Association of Museums-Museum Studies Committee, 1975-1978 (Box 26)
  - Minutes of the Conference on Museum Training Programs, 1972
- Historical Background, 1862-1989
  The Historical Background series (1862-1989; 0.2 linear ft.) is largely material gathered by museum staff in preparation for the 1986 exhibition celebrating the UMMA's fortieth anniversary. The majority of these documents are photocopies though there are two manuscripts relating to the museum's history, one written in 1951 and the other in 1970, in the 'General' file. Also part of this series are files on directors and assistant directors which contain curricula vitae and publicity of new appointments and/or resignations.
  - Acquisitions history (Box 26)
  - Advisory Board, 1954-1956 (Box 26)
  - Clippings, 1862-1985 (Box 26)
  - General, 1951-1992 (Box 26)
  - Photographs (Box 26)
  - Statements of purpose, 1930-1956 (Box 26)
  - Study Committee, 1954-1956 (Box 26)
  - Directors/Assistant Directors
    - Paul Grigaut (Box 26)
    - William Hennessey (includes Director search), 1989 (Box 26)
    - Mary Kujawski (Box 26)
    - Evan Maurer (Box 26)
    - Jean Paul Slusser (Box 26)
    - Graham Smith (Box 26)
    - Bret Waller (Box 26)
- Docents, 1984-2002
  The Docents series (1984-2002; 0.3 linear ft.) includes a limited amount of material documenting museum tours and other docent-sponsored events. The 'Recognition/Awards' file contains a pin designed after the UMMA's sculpture Nydia, The Blind Flower Girl of Pompeii given to docents who had achieved emeritus status from 1993-2000. Also within this series are photographs of members of several docent classes in the late 1980s and early 1990s.
  - Clippings, 1984-1997 (Box 27)
  - Tours, 1993-2002 (Box 27)
  - Recognition/Awards, 1986-1993 (Box 27)
  - Photographs, 1988-1995; undated; 3 folders (Box 27)
- Sound Recordings
  [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
  - Photography Lectures
    - Walker Evans Photography, Lecture, 1971; Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
      - [Side 1; no Side 2], [0475-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Talk by Walker Evans in connection with the Walker Evans Photography exhibition (Oct. 27 - Dec. 5, 1971).)
    - Walker Evans Photography, Old, 1971 October 29; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [0475-SR-2-1]; mp3 file; (Walker Evans discusses art and artists, their relationships with society and faith.)
    - Walker Evans Photography, New, 1971 October 29; Audio Reel-to-Reel
      - [Part 1], [0475-SR-3-1]; mp3 file; (Walker Evans discusses his life and his own connection art.)
    - The Impact of Photography on Other Forms of Two Dimensional Art, 1976 March 26; Audio Reel-to-Reel
      - [Part 1], [0475-SR-4-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion of “The Impact of Photography on Other Forms of Two Dimensional Art,” with Rudolf Arnheim, Philip Davis, Diane Kirkpatrick and Ira Licht (curator, Museum of Contemporary Art Chicago). The discussion complements the exhibition "One Eye View" presently on view in the museum.)
      - [Part 2], [0475-SR-4-2]; mp3 file; (Discussion of “The Impact of Photography on Other Forms of Two Dimensional Art,” with Rudolf Arnheim, Philip Davis, Diane Kirkpatrick and Ira Licht (curator, Museum of Contemporary Art Chicago). The discussion complements the exhibition "One Eye View" presently on view in the museum.)
Related Material
Researchers may also be interested in the personal papers of several early museum leaders which can be found at the Bentley Historical Library:
Paul L. Grigaut papers, 1929-1969
Charles Henry Sawyer papers, 1930-1966
Jean Paul Slusser papers, 1905-1978